<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors on Andrés V Data Portfolio</title>
    <link>https://andresvdata.github.io/portfolio/authors/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Authors on Andrés V Data Portfolio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://andresvdata.github.io/portfolio/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://andresvdata.github.io/portfolio/authors/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://andresvdata.github.io/portfolio/authors/admin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, I&amp;rsquo;m Andres Viloria 👋&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find excitement in the world of data—unraveling its stories and unlocking hidden treasures is what I do best! My journey began as an engineer, where I honed my skills in understanding, processing, and bringing data to life. Now, I&amp;rsquo;m on an exhilarating path as a data scientist, driven by a passion for turning raw information into valuable insights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve got a great track record when it comes to understanding, cleaning up, and making data look amazing. I&amp;rsquo;m like a wizard with programming languages—SQL, R, and Python are my secret potions for talking to computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools like SQL Server Management Studio, Jupyter Notebook, Power BI, SSIS, Anaconda, and IBM Cloud are my sidekicks. They help me turn boring data into exciting insights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a team player with a sharp mind and a get-things-done attitude. Put me in a group, and I&amp;rsquo;ll help us reach our goals while making sure our work shines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, I&amp;rsquo;m expanding my skills with the Data Analytics program at Langara College. It&amp;rsquo;s like adding more tools to my data toolkit, making me even better at what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
