<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors on </title>
    <link>https://andresvdata.github.io/authors/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Authors on </description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://andresvdata.github.io/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://andresvdata.github.io/authors/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://andresvdata.github.io/authors/admin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Passionate about the potential of data and its applications, I hold a Post Degree Diploma in Data Analytics. Proficient in utilizing tools like Python, R, Tableau, Power BI, and PostgreSQL, I have gained practical experience in exciting collaborative projects involving predicting trends, sorting data, and understanding human language using Natural Language Processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout my journey, I collaborated with real companies to solve genuine problems. By partnering with them, we improved their understanding of customers and efficiently managed large volumes of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having worked with various organizations over time, I have acquired skills in multiple programming languages and data tools. For instance, my experience at Softgic equipped me with expertise in data transformation, web development, and databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recognized for my creative thinking, I am dedicated to continuous learning and strongly believe in the power of teamwork, leadership, and effective communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benefiting from an engineering background, my logical and problem-solving abilities have been enhanced.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
